# Curriculum Vitae Martin Jansen

Duisburg, Germany/Nijmegen, Netherlands

m.p.jansen@icloud.com

Website: http://martinpjansen.github.io

ResearchGate: <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Martin-Jansen-5">https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Martin-Jansen-5</a>

Open Science Framework: <a href="https://osf.io/crhn5/">https://osf.io/crhn5/</a> LinkedIn: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/martinpjansen/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/martinpjansen/</a>

#### Research interests

During my bachelor education, which focused on marketing and sales, my interests for the underlying psychological mechanisms in these areas started to grow. Therefore, I have chosen to broaden my vision and started a master degree in communication science. During my master studies I have developed a particular interest in research, consumer behavior and culture and innovations in communication, and this motivated me to start working as a research assistant while finishing my master. Given this background, I am now advancing my understanding of consumer behavior, innovations in communication and their impact on society trough a PhD at the University of Duisburg-Essen in which I investigate the effects of transparency measures regarding microtargeting in the political environment.

#### Education

2020-present	Doctor of Philosophy, Social Psychology: Media and Communication
	University of Duisburg-Essen
2019-2020	Master of Science, Communication Science (Specialization:
	Commercial Communication)
	,
	Radboud University Nijmegen
2017-2019	Pre-master Communication Science
	Radboud University Nijmegen
2019	Post-Bachelor Sales and Account management (post-hbo)
2019	Your Ability Business School
	Tour Aduly Business School
2012 2017	
2012-2017	Bachelor of Commercial Economics)
	HAN University of Applied Sciences
2008-2012	Secondary Vocational Education Facility Management
	ROC Nijmegen
	no c riginegen

## **Work Experience**

· · or ir Emperionee	
2020-present	Researcher/PhD Student, Social Psychology: Media and Communication, Department of Computer Science and Applied Cognitive Science, Faculty of Engineering. Part of the Research Hub for Human-Centered Media and Technology University of Duisburg-Essen
2018-2019	Account manager, responsible for analytics, customer contracts, appointments with clients, and lead nurturing Suez Recycling and Recovery Netherlands
2018	Tutor for high-school students in Mathematics, English, Economics Maakwijzer Nijmegen
2018	Sales Agent, responsible for direct sales for museums and not for profit organizations  Fonky Sales Nijmegen
2012-2015	Bar/team responsible, active at professional soccer club N.E.C. Nijmegen 68 Degrees

#### Peer reviewed articles

**Jansen, M.**, Meier, Y., & Krämer, N.C. (In review) Time for transparent targeting: Effects of disclosing microtargeting on coping mechanisms, credibility, and political attitude. *Communication Research*.

**Jansen, M.**, & Krämer, N.C. (In review) The effects of targeting disclosure labels on credibility and trustworthiness for micro-targeted political advertisements. *Weizenbaum Journal of the Digital Society*.

Wischnewski, M., Ngo, T., Bernemann, R., **Jansen, M.**, & Krämer, N. (2022). "I agree with you, bot!" How users (dis)engage with social bots on Twitter. *New Media & Society*. https://doi.org/10.1177/14614448211072307

Ngo, T., Wischnewski, M., Bernemann, R., **Jansen, M.**, & Krämer, N.C. (In review). Spot the Bot: How Users Detect Social Bots and Use Profile Verification Tools on Twitter. *Computers in Human Behaviour*.

#### **Academic conferences**

## **Conference presentations**

**Jansen, M.**, & Krämer, N.C. (2022, May) *The effects of targeting disclosure labels on credibility and trustworthiness for micro-targeted political advertisements*. Paper presented at the 72<sup>nd</sup> annual conference of the International Communication Association, Paris, France.

**Jansen, M.**, & Krämer, N.C. (2022, February) *The effects of targeting disclosure labels on credibility and trustworthiness for micro-targeted political advertisements*. Paper presented at the 24<sup>th</sup> annual 24 hours of Communication Science of the Netherlands - Flanders Communication Association (NeFCA), Brussels, Belgium.

Wischnewski, M., Ngo, T., Bernemann, R., **Jansen, M.**, & Krämer, N.C. (2021, September). "*I agree with you, bot!*" *How users (dis)engage with social bots on Twitter*. Poster presented at the 12<sup>th</sup> Media Psychology Conference, Aachen, Germany.

Ngo, T., Wischnewski, M., Bernemann, R., **Jansen, M.**, & Krämer, N.C. (2021, September). *Spot the Bot: How Users Detect Social Bots and Use Profile Verification Tools on Twitter.* Poster presented at the 12<sup>th</sup> Media Psychology Conference, Aachen, Germany.

## **Conference panels**

"DGPuk Panel: Political Targeting During the German Federal Election." Panel at the 72<sup>nd</sup> annual conference of the International Communication Association, Paris, France, May 2022

## **Research Experience**

2020-present

Researcher/PhD Candidate

Social Psychology: Media and Communication. University of Duisburg

Essen

During this occupation I plan, carry out and complete studies, teach/support teaching activities and contribute to interdisciplinary workgroups (Social Bots on Twitter; Influencers in Social Media).

2020-2020

Research assistant of Dr. B. Müller

Radboud University

Responsible for preparation, organization, and data collection of three studies: one experimental study on the influence of stereotypes on teacher evaluations in higher education, a study on the influence of non-verbal imitation on resistance in a virtual reality context and a study on the influence of attitude (un)certainty on self-persuasion.

2019-2020

Master Thesis

The effects of personalization trough augmented reality on perceived value and users buying intentions in retail.

Supervised by Prof. Dr. T. Bosse.

Conducting an experimental study on the effects of personalization on perceived benefits and perceived privacy risks and the effect of value on buying intention.

2019-2020

Research in a Professional Context (Master course)

Together with 3 fellow students, I conducted a focus group study on the recruitment of new students for Helicon schools.

Supervised by Dr. P. Nelissen.

2017 Bachelor Thesis focused on market research on modular part-time

education for the faculty of education at the HAN University of Applied

Sciences. Supervised by F. Croes, MSc.

**Teaching experience** 

2020- present Teaching multiple courses in the applied cognitive and media sciences

master, supervising bachelor theses.

University of Duisburg-Essen

2020- 2020 Teaching a bachelor course on quantitative research methods and how

to start and conduct research to a group of first year communication

students.

HAN University of Applied Sciences.

**Society memberships** 

2022- present PhD Representative for the Media Psychology division of the

Netherlands-Flanders Communication Association (NeFCA)

2019-2020 Member of the sponsor committee of student basketball association

N.S.B.V. Trajanum

2016 Member of the sounding board group for the design of the minor: Sales

and key account management for the HAN University of Applied

Sciences

2012-2017 Student member of the Sales Management Association (SMA)

#### Courses/Summer schools

Introduction to R programming, July 2022

Data Science Summer School – Hertie School Berlin

Statistics and probability for data science, August 2022

Data Science Summer School – Hertie School Berlin

# Certificates

Data Science: R Basics, Harvard University via edX

Basic principles of online marketing, Google

Senior Sales Professional, Sales Management Association

Customer oriented phone contact, Kenneth Smith

Referee (F), Dutch Basketball Association

## Software

SPSS, R, Jamovi, JASP, MAXQDA, Inquisit, Excel, Microsoft PowerBI,

# Languages

Dutch (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (moderate)